Hello, good morning. Can you hear me? Thank you. Great, great. Yeah. We may wait for one minute.
what's helpful versus harmful, what's true versus false,
objective, maximum reward during your generation process.
change the writing style or improve the reasoning.
The first one is post training quantization.
Third one is reward hacking.
then it overrides the other capabilities.
There's no changes if you change learning rate. You'll find the optimal learning rate already
This is a serious risk because when the model learns to maximum the reward score,
Because I understand you may make some modifications when you do the demo presentation, right?
So the whole idea of using quantization is try to further reduce the original
This is, we start, we will do the same thing with pre-trained model,
So this table leads some ways to prevent
or what's appropriate versus offensive,
Maybe SFT using Laura or Qlora might be a choice.
So one type of interaction with LM is,
Okay. I think we can start. As usual, if you have any questions during the lecture, please
because just now we mentioned in the 4K limitations
the catastrophic forgetting.
then you can go inside to adjust rank and
train, do the SFT and alignment.
Condition is you have the data.
that's the only objective of this model.
So it will be good to submit the source code together with them if that works for you.
memory
For example, you can tune the learning rate,
requirement for the big models in order to make the
And also, if that's still not fulfilled, your task alignment might be another choice.
to get the best performance on your training data. So this is an empirical
during the SFT, the objective is just to minimize the loss.
raise up your hand or message me in the chat. Okay, let's get started. So today's topic is about
Then we get a model. After this, we will do,
you can do less epochs,
It may find some loophole.
as I said, one game for Mario.
parameter efficient fine tuning
But of course, if you want to submit earlier, that's very welcome.
It will directly find the shortest path to go to the best reward.
we will use some data to compute the quantization method,
and you can manipulate your data.
It does not give those information on harmful or not,
We give it a prompt.
works mostly. So that's the idea of parameter
strategy for
You can choose alignment method to suit your task.
And also, we can do parameter efficient fight tuning.
Then the LM generates some action.
I will make announcement in the next slide to let everyone know about this.
using law-run for fine tuning just for your information.
for example.
large language model adaptation. Today's lecture we will show how to adapt
then quantize the network and run inference.
efficient fine tuning. We introduced Laura and Kyu Laura.
So that brings us to further training.
But sometimes it's not a good quality for output.
So that means put it in a simple word,
That means give your response.
Of course, you still need data. You need to have data.
So this staged approach
So this actually, which is Laura,
This is called alignment.
Then how the response is given is based on the LM weights inside the model.
That's the called reward hacking.
Any questions?
pre-train models to specific tasks and behaviors. So this is a learning outcome for today.
So the goal of the alignment is to teach
let me train a model as usual, then after a base model train, we do quantization.
instead of tuned all the parameters
Sorry for the confusion.
On the other hand, if your problem is not in the performance, you are looking at the efficiency like the speed.
Okay, then I will continue. So this is our first topic for today.
The last one will be human annotation because we all need human preference,
this is the most effective medication
at the same time this stage approach
the model human values across these three dimensions.
Don't worry, I will make announcement.
So the whole objective is to maximize the human preference.
for catastrophic forgetting.
saves some time and
Then I will let Professor No and make announcement there.
The next method is called quantization aware training.
You may want to use this to check your understanding after the lecture. Here is the outline for today.
avoids like
A helpful, I mean, it needs to follow
So here is the key method
Next one, we will move to the second topic of this lecture, which is instruction tuning.
the pair of bad or good data pairs.
too many combinations during the training steps.
That means we simultaneously do quantization and find meaning at the same time.
That's a whole idea.
So quantization is one of the directions you can look for.
Thank you. Any other questions?
users' instructions, right?
we are going to discuss in this lecture.
So it's expensive when you need a huge amount of this kind of data.
The simulation of LM alignment versus reinforcement learning.
And harmless means the large lung remodel
Please take time to do the survey. Thank you.
Also, sometimes we call it supervised fine tuning or SFT.
We will first introduce our motivation why we do fine tuning. Then we will move roughly in the order
Okay, just now we showed the how to tune the parameters for Laura, but
Because this one will freeze the original weights
So you can look for a smaller model, which is quantized.
should refuse unsive requests.
So you need to do the training of those models.
and only train a small tiny adapters like here.
So those are challenges of RIL attract in lecture model training.
Okay, if no more questions, that's all for today. Thank you very much.
I hope you are still following me.
Or you can load a library that do the quantization online.
Because just now we mentioned Laura and Kyu Laura. Those methods address
what kind of width we should apply Laura to. So this
So here in the table below,
Instead of only do SFT or alignment,
So it won't the original model,
Now we almost understand the reward model.
we show an example of harmful content.
that presenting our motivation. Then go through how and LM models is built from raw pre-training to
So those are choices you can make.
So that's why some simpler alternative for PPO is proposed.
this is the
the training process will also remember those quantization objectives at the same time.
how to fine tune a model efficiently. This method
model is still keep its own weights without changes.
Maybe in the early initial version of large lung remodel,
So that's the general guideline.
this is the numbers from the original Laura paper. So it compares this table, the top table,
It's an important indicator for LM during the learning process.
You start from three and the easy method.
When we train this, it will only be used in the inference steps.
Today we'll only discuss about DPO and GRPO,
address those questions. But supervised fine tuning or SFT address
it does not do, it might answer you these questions,
Then until you get what you want, then you can stop there.
model refinement and the lastly optimization. I would also like to provide some strategy for you
So the model learns to account for quantization noise.
compares the performance across different width types.
which are very popular use in the alignment process.
but currently the recent models,
So if you in the future, you want the model to do another task,
But how do we get the reward model?
You don't need to go through all the steps.
would to train the model to do. So specifically, SFT is how we transform a raw
So in this way, usually this quantization aware training will be much more complex,
You can see we can Laura mostly applied on the attention width. So that's a value
So that's the key information I want to convey here.
the good models should not answer those kinds of questions
So firstly, let's look at this direct preference optimization.
you can just replace this adapter.
We need human preference.
to consider when you face this fine tuning scenario. Okay, okay here. This slide shows the
So that's the beauty of the Laura.
That's the idea we want the large length model to learn from.
Okay, that's all the topics I want to cover for today.
the pretrend model into another one that follows human instruction in a meaningful way.
and it should answer something like this.
The key differences from PPO is it does not need reward model.
Okay, let's get into it.
because you know it will consider about quantization loss during the training.
So this means harmless.
query key value metrics and sometimes on the WO which is output width.
Parameter efficient fight tuning.
But how do we get human preference?
This is the reference.
Another objective is to train the large lung model,
So the key inside behind PFT,
If you are interested, please go through some links, especially those many original papers describe all these methods.
So let's see how can we do that? What do I mean on that? Here is an example
Here we give some example.
But usually the accuracy will be better than this one,
what a rack and agent system can and cannot do. In our previous lectures in the previous week,
be honest.
It's not easy as Mario to get a coin plus one,
So from this paper you can look for the you can understand the details of this
So it directly instead of using a reward model every time to decide what reward you can get.
So it should admit, it cannot do something.
which is parameter efficient fight tuning,
but there's pros and cons for each method.
And instead of just give up,
is that the weight updates during the fight tuning are low rank.
of why instruction tuning is necessary. For example, we ask a question.
bomb, bomb, bomb, minus 10k.
results, but the
Okay, so now I want to talk about the tutorial today.
So it QAT, which is quantization aware training,
generate something directly.
we saw how rack and agent help solve several key problems that's given model access to external
finding is that I've that adapting both
This is not strict forward like that.
It directly using the preference data,
So this is called parameter efficient.
So we also have an example here,
Explain the moon landing to a six year old in a few sentences. So this, if you give this question
Because we are dealing with natural language.
query query and the value width will give you best overall performance.
Because imagine this example,
the score of the pairs of preference data to get the reward,
That's how I already mentioned this today's tutorial is to show you how to do alignment using DPO.
typically yields better accuracy,
answer to this.
It's not like...
That means I'm not sure about this,
suppose in the original model,
but it requires additional training time and resources,
but it does not just give you answers anyhow.
and real-time knowledge, also in enabling multi-step reasoning with some tools and also reducing
So that that's one
we have a weight matrix,
We don't have universal accepted reward for each question and answer.
to a base model, which is trained by raw pre-training. Remember the three steps we introduced
which is d times k,
findings from this table.
Remember DPO is a better choice than PPO because it has less models to handle.
So that's the reason why we need alignment here.
which we as a practitioner on AI, we may not have.
to infer the reward of the different choices.
while d is the input dimension.
The bottom table here, this is to ask what is optimal rank for this
For example, we give d 1000,
hallucination and factual queries. But there are do have something that rack and agent still can't do.
We want to solve,
In that case, things we do not have a golden answer for each question.
So usually this PTQ is relatively more popular way to do the quantization.
just now. The first step of large length remodel training is using raw data to do a pre-training,
they teach the model those human values here.
So here, PPO measures how much the model improves
And it directly it does not need a reward model.
then k is output dimension,
different tasks.
which is 5,000 here in this example.
There's harmful, harmless, and honest.
So it directly use your data to do the reward estimation.
The finally the paper is tries different ranks. So if we still remember what's
What can we do?
You can look at the list here. Overall, we can think of it in this way.
at choosing the good answer compared to its original model version.
So that's the idea of why we need alignment.
Altogether for this weight matrix,
We can do comparison.
Okay, the next optimization on the model is called knowledge distillation.
during these pre-training steps, you get a base model. If you ask this question to that base model,
Instead of giving an answer to each question,
we will need how many parameters.
You can go through the code to find out more.
rank for if a higher rank means you need to find you more parameters.
Oh, here we have another one is called verbosity.
So the data here sets how far the model is allowed to drift from its original style.
We can see we just did times k,
we will give each question to answers.
rack gives the model better notes to read before an examination. For example, LM is a student,
It shows how to the task is to change the way that LM answers your question, the format of the answers.
So exactly do another kind of model compression.
This, for example, if you give an instruction,
that's 5 million parameters,
you can see some of the response here. The base model actually did not answer the question.
One is a good one, one is a bad one.
Lower rank means smaller parameters you need to tune.
just for this matrix.
Instead of just looking at which those with values,
like this, if you give a question,
So in that case, we collect a bunch of questions.
But remember, we learned in linear algebra,
for example. So rack gives the model some notes to read before an examination. But it doesn't make
So those are some hyper parameters.
So the findings in this table shows Laura already performs competitively quite well
it will give you very long answers,
Then for each question, we will give human preferred answer and human not preferred answer.
So instead of that, it would be that it just do a text completion. So it's doing
So this is just a tutorial for your reference.
The sigma is the sigma function, which we are very familiar with.
the matrix can be decomposed.
it's train, it used the original model, the trained model as a teacher,
So imagine we decomposed this matrix into two smaller ones,
the models matter automatically. It depends on the quality of the model itself. If the model
From this week, we don't have new labs for you.
but instead,
So all in all, when RIL HRF remembers the PPO needs four models in memory.
with a very small like even R equals one or two. That means you only need to find you two small
In this way, we can see this data can be used to treat the reward model for a large length model.
a brief answer or concise answer will be preferred.
to do a knowledge transfer to a student model.
like a text completion tasks, generate more words after your initial problems. So this is because
Please concentrate on finishing the previous slides and use your time for addition and group project.
which is d times k and d times r and r times d.
So that's, we also need the model to understand.
So usually the student model can be as in different structure or in same structure,
is a bad writer, you just add extra data to it. It won't make it a good one. Also, if we can't do
But DPO only needs two, the original model and the model to be trained.
Here, this r is far less than k here.
one or two dimension column vectors. You can already achieve good results for certain tasks.
In today's tutorial,
At least the large length model gets to learn what's good, what's bad.
You have already done so.
but less complex like a teacher model.
during the pre-training language models, you remember they just do the
we will give you an example of how to train a large lung model
Next, I want to give you, because you may only have about two weeks to the deadline of the group projects, right?
This chart may be not that obvious,
So it significantly reduced memory needs during the training.
but r should be very much smaller than k,
Because usually in this knowledge distillation,
using alignment approach, which is a DPO.
some reasoning through multiple steps, for example, given some document to read,
So in that way, it somehow follows human preference on a good answer.
give you the training strategy is a text completion tasks. So given the input,
we want a student model to learn from the teacher,
We will train the model to follow the instruction
the dimension here.
So these are some practical guidelines to follow in your own finding your new experiment if you are
I have read your progress report one by one.
So you can see if we use linear algebra,
but it's more specific on certain tasks.
may not help that much as well. Right? So that's why when arch-language model is not able to
So it's far more memory efficient and easy to train in a model training practice.
So that's the idea of collecting data for alignment for the large length model during alignment process.
to generate answers in certain format.
the model strategy is to find the suitable with most high
with times, we multiply these two matrix,
So that's the tutorial.
I think all of you have a good progress.
doing that kind of training. Just now we showed Laura. Laura is a good mechanism to train
That means you, sometimes after training, this distillation process,
we can still convert into a matrix,
At least you fulfilled some tasks in your mission in your progress report.
Maybe you want to try out.
So in our tutorial, we use this method to show you how to teach the large length model
probability of following words. So that's why the behavior is like this. So the
perform well in certain tasks, fine-tune the model is presented for your consideration.
d times k, right?
the student model actually can perform better in certain tasks
Okay, just now we talk about alignment,
So that's sorry, here,
Let's look at the famous human-relevant information learning from human feedback.
why we need alignment, right?
I have a mistake here,
So please continue working on that, but remind full of the deadline.
Because we want our model to have the same value
to find you a large lengthing model with very small amount of parameters and yet we achieve
than the original teacher model.
to output in certain direction, in certain format.
the model are just trained to predict the next token after the token you give. So they are not
it should be k here.
Actually fine-tuning actually changes the model's internal parameters. So using the example we
So this is normal because a student model
Sorry, I will change that in the PDF,
This is originally proposed by the OpenAI in chat GPT.
So that's DPO.
as human preference.
are more not as general as teacher,
And I want to highlight the submissions.
Another one is called GRPO.
good performance. But
But how do we do the alignment, actually?
GRPO is actually proposed by DeepSick.
to instruct, instructed to respond the question well. So that's why we will need
it should be a k here.
but it's more specialized.
So this is how do we do?
discussed just now, it's like putting the model through some specialized training on your own tasks.
imagine if you have a very big foundation model that means the original model is quite big.
So, sorry, after that,
So for, remember, we need to submit presentation, videos and support.
That's what we can conclude here.
So the story need to start with reinforcement learning.
When DeepSick R1 is come out last year before,
otherwise it cannot go back to the original dimension.
Firstly, remember just now we have talked about the SFT and base LM training.
Usually that's the way of distillation,
So in this alignment scenario,
to use instruction tuning to teach the model to answer questions to follow our instructions.
So it should be a k here,
Even we use Laura we can use Laura to train a small model. At the beginning we still need to
So it likely the model after training will do better in those tasks that it does not perform very well
So for presentation and video, the presentation slides usually will be used in your video recording, I guess.
here is correct.
because it's a usually student model is optimized for certain domain.
so GRPO become one of the most used policy optimization method during alignment alignment.
reinforcement learning is one of the more used approach
So after base LM training, large amount of data,
Then just now we mentioned,
we do a metric decomposition into these two small metrics.
So that's why the instruction instruction tuning or SFT is trained the model
load the base model into the memory in order to do in the training process. So in that case
and that's why we need to talk about it first.
So that's why sometimes it gets better performance.
and we use SFT to teach the model to answer questions,
so that's the reasoning why we want to have fine-tuning in certain scenarios.
So imagine what's in reinforcement learning.
So this is how GRPO works.
So in that presentation video, we will encourage every team members to speak.
Just an example here, we have some models called distill birth.
Then let's calculate how many parameters we have,
because we just compared this is not enough.
on the instruction on response pairs. So we give the model some questions and answer pairs
even you use Laura to find you it is still challenging. So in this scenario we introduce
It removes one model, which is a value model from the original people.
This is widely used in game industry, for example.
if we give these two small metrics.
So that's why we need alignment.
Before we go into the details of fine-tuning, let's ask the most important question,
So this is actually a distill version of birth.
It's not required, but we hope every team members who contributed should speak to present your project.
So then suppose r equals five only,
So next, we will go to the alignment process.
for it to learn. And if the model gets enough amount of data, get many exposure on this kind
It is 40% smaller than the original birth model,
So instead of learning a value function,
In the alignment process, firstly, we will need a reward model,
Q Laura. That means we we we quantize the base model. Q Laura Q is quantization here. So we
I think many of us may know this game, right?
should you do fine-tuning at all? So we can use this kind of tree like reference.
then we have, for these metrics,
This is Mario, Super Mario.
how many parameters we have is d times r, right?
but it runs 60% faster,
you just generate multiple responses, average them,
because remember the Mario case, Mario, the action of Mario,
So that's a good practice for you as well.
of scenario. The model will learn how to answer a question properly. So that's the basic,
and also it achieves almost 97% of performance as the original model.
The idea of this Super Mario is he goes through a long, long pass
So that's all the cells in these metrics.
then use that average as a value baseline.
And also, when you do the presentation, your face is optional.
quantize the original model. The original huge model usually they stored in like 60
all depends on how much reward he will get, right?
So this is the steps how the GRPO works.
Imagine you have a task, right? If it requires external or real-time knowledge,
And for these metrics,
then every time he sees a coin and he gets it,
So you can imagine, although a small loss on the performance,
we have r times k here.
the most important training method to train a large model to follow human instructions.
So he needs to maximize the rewards during the process.
You don't need to have to show your face in the video.
So all together,
You can also search for the GRPO papers or some explanations.
he will get points.
if we use the same value here,
16-bit or 32-bit kind of wheat matrices. But if we quantize the model to 4-bit precision
but the big gain on the efficiency of the inference.
He will get reward.
So similarly, for a large length model, we teach like the length model.
Maybe a screen recording voiceover is fine.
then you can consider your server's system. But if it doesn't need that,
we'll get 30k parameters.
Then if he bumped into a, this is a mushroom,
So the power of instruction tuning is the training data must be very diverse. Otherwise,
But the core idea is that it do not need a value model.
And about content, it's better to focus on the key point of your project, right?
So this distillation is ideal for production deployments,
So compare with the original five million parameters.
right, if bumped into a gumbah, he will be penalized.
We firstly need to let it know what's the reward.
or we'll go through this branch, it doesn't need external knowledge, but needs new behavior
and the model size can be significantly reduced. So that's the idea of Laura.
Here, we only use less than one percent of the original parameters
So we use the human preference data.
It just uses this way to estimate the advantage.
His life will be deducted, something like that.
we only be able to answer certain type of questions. So I would like to prepare our training
You need to clearly summarize the problem, the approach and what's the result and maybe the reflection as well.
when latency and memory are constrained.
or writing scale. Then you need to ask yourself another question, do you have training data,
Just now we mentioned for each question, we gave a good answer versus a bad answer.
So that's the game scenario.
to represent the original metrics.
If you still remember in PPO,
Laura Q Laura. Sorry. So one way is through quantization. Another mechanism is
So this is a very popular approach.
advantage is calculate the accumulated award until this pass in current status.
So the goal of the game is he pass through all the pass
So this is the mass behind this law.
So in this case, we used those data to train the large length remodel
And for the submission, here are some notes for your to consider.
or do you have enough budget to use all these GPU resources? If yes,
In some open source models, you can see,
data. We will need a wide variety of instructions. And then the model learns a generalize for
and get as small as enough coins
pitched optimizer optimizers. This means if during the training right because you need to load
it provides several different models like distills, something.
If the file size is so small, too big, you can provide a gate handling, but the remains for to make it can be accessed by us.
to learn the preference of human.
So why does this work?
So this is how GRPO works.
and try to not lose his life to bump on a gumbah.
okay, you can do fine-tuning. If not, if these two questions are not,
Because the empirical findings from the original law of paper
So for example, DIFSEC also have several distilled versions.
So this is called re-inversement learning from human feedback, RIOHF.
instruction follow capability. For example, here, these two examples on screen shows the diversity
this guy and also two small B and A matrix during the training right. If your GPU or your hardware
So eventually GRPO only needs three models instead of four.
you better try further from engineering. We have taught in the first lecture of this second half.
is that fine tuning,
So that's the whole idea.
when we do fine tuning,
So this is a whole idea of the reward, the re-inversement learning for a large length model.
Those applications that require less memory and good latency,
So this scenario is easily can be
it only updates some low dimensionality.
You can make it public or you can make it private, but you can ask, you can ask for our GitHub account.
So that's why it is more stable during training.
of the task. The first one is a creative writing task. And the next one is a like a form filing
So this is the first checkpoint you need to consider when you go deep in the fine-tuning.
So many of the updates only clustered in the low rank subspace.
gets full away during the training process the pitched optimizer will shift from those do not
simulate use reinforcement learning.
And some models, for example, DeepSick R1,
Here, you can see the reward is the human preference.
so you can choose from.
The reinforcement learning, the idea is you have a state.
So that's why we believe this decomposition,
So this is about knowledge distillation.
The key message is here. Fine-tuning is not always the right answer. It comes with cost
achieves better reasoning skills using GRPO.
task. So if a model trained across many such tasks, it will again, brought instruction follow
So each state is a scenario like he's in this position
If you want to make a private link just for your information on the submission.
Another method for optimization of the model is called mixer of expert or MOE.
And the policy here is the large length model.
still can be the enough adaptation.
That's why this method is being adopted by many recent large hand models.
needed during the disk step of training. You will move those pages which are not currently
This is a model we want to adapt and learn to follow the human instruction.
and what's the front, what's the, what's the,
To move the original model to a desired direction.
and complex complexity. So be careful when you decide to do this.
And in order for us to please give a self-explanatory written about how to install, how to run it, like a user manual or something.
ability that transferred to a new unseen tasks. So that's the whole idea behind the instruction
So this is, we can think of this as an example.
is there a coin and what's the environment,
So beyond this PPO, GRPO, DQ,
required to move them into CPU so that it will save your GPU for the current computation. Then in
Of course, there are many optimization ways to optimize to change the width of the LM.
something like this.
there are many other new methods.
For example, this is the, this picture is one frame.
So let's understand the full FM training pipeline from scratch. This tree illustrates
We can think of it as we have a medical clinic.
So let's summarize the parameter equation fine tuning.
tuning. You prepare a wild variety of instruction and answer pairs. That's very important for instruction
I won't go through them, but you just need to know.
So in every frame, there is a policy.
Instead of we have one journalist, Dr. Ho-Hendel.
the next step if those data will be used it will revert back to the GPU memory. So that this is the
So one popular way is called PPO, which is proximal policy optimization.
Policy is the decision making mechanism like
For example, ORPO is particularly very efficient
the three stages training pipeline. So every major large-length of the model we are using
It's like you are storing a high resolution photo,
And also someone asked about API keys because underneath you might use several paid APIs for larger and green models.
Ho-Hendel's everything.
fine tuning. So this slides give up before and after comparison of supervised fine tuning.
we, inside we have a probability model.
for example, a full HD photo d times k in these resolutions.
You have a set, you have multiple specialists,
because it only needs one model.
today, follow, kindly follow these three steps. The first step is called pre-training.
So this is one of the most early policy, which is used in chat GPT.
two key strategy of using Q Laura to further help the parameter efficient fine tuning. Here we have
Besides the Mario will go to which direction.
It actually can combine the SFT and alignment in a single process.
specialists, which for example, cardiologists, neuro-aligists,
It can do up, left and right.
You are not required to share them, but please point us how to give those API keys when we want to run those code.
We can store a compressed version,
So you can see what has been changed during the sft. It teaches the model how to
So this is the most expensive and one-time step done by only by those large
So that's all Mario can go,
which is these two small ones,
Remember, just now at the beginning,
So we will firstly introduce this PPO.
another for pediatrition.
but each, each direction has different probabilities here.
we show the large hand model training
but we can still capture the important changes during this process.
illustration of compare the Laura and Q Laura. One is the precision of the parameters. Another is
You can see I won't go to very detail of this PPO policy optimization, but just give you an idea.
usually involves three steps.
So each expert will only handle certain types of patients.
respond to instructions, not as before, just predict the next token. So that's her key differences.
organizations, like large labs, large companies, because it costs millions of dollars and use
So this is the original model,
But if you use ORPO, it will do the step two and three together.
So this is another consideration for your submission.
So that's the mass behind the borax.
the original model, the Mario can use
So as a beginning, each patient is routed to the right specialists
Let's look at more details.
pitched optimizer. You can look for more details using these people. Then we have a question.
like trailing tokens to do it. So usually small enterprise, small companies cannot do it.
So that's a very efficient way to train a large hand model.
So just for your information, you lay every year or have some events to showcase our student project.
when it goes through these games.
Given a original model, it will PPO will require four models to restore four models inside the Mary.
On the left here, before sft, we have a base model. It will give us this question,
We compare the regular fine tuning versus lower here.
to do the proper checking consultation.
So here the very important point is a reward.
So this is just for your information.
These two diagrams make a very good contrast.
So if your project are done well and you have a very good demo, your video may be selected to showcase at ICT events.
Just now we mentioned, if Mario gets a coin,
So as AI practitioners, we typically start from stage two.
And also, a simple PPO also needs one single model.
explain what photo sensitivities is. It replied with no structure and totally does not understand the
So that's a similar idea for mixture of experts.
Just now we mentioned about quantization. So what is quantization? So the core idea of quantization
In regular fine tuning,
he will be awarded, he will get some coin
we directly update the full width metrics.
It removes the original throws a model.
So the first one will be the original model.
So this, usually, this graph shows how it works.
and he will get some life or something.
Sorry, take a pre-training based model and we do fine-tuning on it.
is quite simple. Here we give an example here. For example we have original weights
So it's in the same dimension as the pre-tuned width here.
intent of the question. So here are some drawbacks of this kind of answers. But after sft,
For example, the big events may be open house, day zero, something like that.
It saves the memory and simplifies the training process.
Yeah, so this reward is a mechanism to decide.
This is the model before training.
So you have a very huge model.
And the stage three is alignment. This is what transforms a technically
So another one is the model we want to train from.
So the update will be on this metric is delta w.
This model consists of multiple experts,
We want to give price or penalize action.
I guess you all attend those kind of events before. So it's a good opportunity to show your projects.
For the rest, if you are interested,
So these are two models.
that are in 32 bit or 16 bit. The idea is we want to represent these original weights using only
you can look for them and understand more details.
but during inference, only one of several experts are actually activated.
the instruction in the model is called instructed model. Given the same question, this time,
Another one is called reward model.
You can imagine if we used the example we showed just now,
capable model into a helpful, harmful, harmless and honest assistant. Sorry.
Just now we mentioned reward is one of the most important parts of training the large length remodel.
Because of our time limitation,
So that's the word, word means in this game.
Maybe you will help to mend the booths where your projects are selected.
or you need to update 5 million of parameters.
I won't go through more details of all the other models.
So here for example, when every time Mario gets coin,
So the rest just keep adult.
In this lecture, we'll cover all three steps, but just to be very in mind that our focus is in
four bits but on the other hand we do not want to lose the precision. So that's our goal.
You can imagine it's very big and also will need a lot of data
model can give a structured more proper answer. So this kind of transformation is remarkable,
So that's the idea of MOE.
Okay, next is some presentation outline for your reference.
And also we have a value model because for each state we need to calculate how much reward we can get from each action.
Any questions?
the reward is a plus one.
No?
But if it goes through the end of the past,
This is compared, we can see this is a sparse model,
in order to do a proper fine tuning.
OK, so now we have go through the three important steps
stage two and three, because this is too expensive. This is beyond asked.
So in quantization this is one type of quantization mechanism called ABS max. So it is
you can see from token prediction to actually instruction following. So that shows the most
This is not a golden like must do thing is just some recommendation for you to consider.
this is a big reward, he will get 10k rewards.
On the other hand, if we use lower,
which is compared to the dense model,
on training a large hand model from the pre-training,
Here, this table shows who can do this and what's the output of those different steps, stages.
So this is called reward model.
instead of computing this delta w directly,
which are no more like large length models.
But if he bump into a gongba,
which is beyond us.
So the value model here is to estimate expected future reward.
So you you are not oblig to follow this steps of this content, but just some recommendations for your consider.
important shift that sft produced. But after the supervised learning like sft, there are sometimes
absolutely max quantization. So we can look at the details. Instead one we look through, we run through
In those dense models, every input will activate all the parameters in the network.
we approximate the 8 using two small metrics.
We cannot control.
that means he will over.
But we are focused on the second and the third steps
So he will be penalized with 10k of points.
Okay, so this table lets you compare across the three stages. Just now we have table shows who can do it,
But on the other hand, these MOE models,
of large hand model training.
That's what we showed just now.
So this means in my case, if he decided to go front, what's the reward he can get?
Of course, if nothing happens,
Which is SFT and alignment.
all the weak values. Then find the maximum values, the minimum and maximum values. So absolute
they only activate a small subset of network.
We call them B and A.
training on label data alone is not enough for modern large-length models. Here, with this
he will not be rewarded or penalized.
We have two smaller metrics.
and what's the output. This table gives you more details of each stages, each training stages.
And last slide will be the teaching feedback module and teaching feedback.
So in SFT, you can use Lora to do parameter efficient training.
So this is a reward function.
So that's, that follows the example I just give.
Both have the R as a rank.
If he decided to go up, what's the reward he can get?
This is very important because every step Mario goes,
Just for your information, it will be good for you to write down what did we do well and what we are not doing well for this module.
four key limitations, even we train and remember for the state, three stage LM training model.
In alignment, you can use many optimization methods
value means the smallest and biggest value. Then we get a range of these values. We know how
So imagine this is a clinic,
So when we multiply these two B and A together,
So in every state, Mary will need to make that calculation.
The key insight for us for AI practitioners is the cost. So the first thing we need to consider
it will depend on the reward.
where you have different specialists to the different stuff.
So every time suppose Mario should do the action
we can still get a metric of in this rank.
like the DPO, JRPO, or the new method I mentioned just now.
So this is calculated using value model.
that maximize the reward.
So that's MOE.
Now we are in the second stage. We already train the model for instruction following,
So during inference,
in this matrix what our maximum and minimum number will be. So we get them into a scale. Then
MOE enables very large model capacity.
is this one. Pre-training is essentially beyond us. So SFT supervised fine-tuning or instruction
So all these methods is to train a large hand model
imagine we trained these two small metrics.
So in the future, this will greatly help us to improve our teaching and also help your juniors.
So same as in LM training here.
So in each state, he needs to find the best action
So that means you have a, for example, I have an MOE model can do everything.
Then during inference,
as we are currently used.
but they're still not enough. Here are the four key limitations. Firstly, this is a label quality
we just add the original weights,
In order to calculate those, we have we have other terminology called advantage.
we can divide this absolute value to all the weights with numbers. So all the numbers will be
that gets the good reward.
Currently, the other large hand model on the market
which is frozen, does not change,
So I appreciate all those who did the feedback for us. Thank you very much.
For example, in this scenario,
But inside here, it consists several small experts can do different things very well
tuning in alignment are absolutely within our reach. You can find you a relatively small model in a
the best action could be jump up, right?
or even open source or not,
and add the new to the multiplication
ceiling. This is obvious, right? Because those models are data dripping. So the quality of the
Because it will get coin here.
I won't give a discuss more here, but advantage is how to decide how to get reward from the reward model and value model.
they are generally follow this training process.
Okay, there are some questions just to some school is do you you can submit together with the others like videos and presentation on do and April tree together.
scaled into minus one to one range. So this is the first step. In the next step we will
of these two small metrics together.
in a specific domain.
And he is quite far from the gongba yet.
So now we want to shift to a broader set
So that's the MOE model.
single computer GPU using Laura parameter efficient fine-tuning. We'll talk about it later.
So after Lora,
model train is significantly based on the data you give. So the annotators quality will decide
So the example is like mixture, deep seek,
He may not bump into gongba after he joked down.
of advanced optimization techniques
the inference time does not increase,
separate these values into several buckets. This depends on how many bits you have. So you can
So that might be the action.
because it's only a addition here.
beyond the fine tuning.
Lamar for you.
Because sometimes when we train a model,
So imagine this is a game, this is only one state.
But on the other hand, we also need to look at the risk flow here.
If you are interested, you can look for the details of how these models are built
So it actually calculates the reward of the whole accumulator reward of the whole past.
the ceiling of the model performance. The second one, no notion of preference. So because the model
It does not change too much on the inference performance or speed.
depends on different scenarios of applications,
and what's the performance for your consideration when you build real applications.
So for for the quiz right for the quiz, it will be in the similar format as the midterm quiz, it will be on site using the examiner.
Our catastrophic forgetting in SFT and reward height in alignment are real failure models. We need to
So going through the games,
So here, the rank R is a very important
the Mario will make multiple decisions
we need to make the models matter and faster and more efficient.
build several buckets to represent all the values between these bucket branch. So this is the
So that you can consider this one is just for this state, but advantage is accumulated one.
So now we almost covered all the concept we want to introduce for today.
based on the objective to maximum the reward.
is doing as sft, the model just gives a question and answer pairs. So it will learn how to produce
Because the whole training in the first three steps
hyper parameter you can control.
consider when we do those. So let's say the major ways to do the fine-tuning. So this graph is from
So a smaller R means of future fewer parameters you need to train.
So that's the goal.
is to make the model perform well.
So the time will also be a when hour around that time. So most question will be an MCQs.
So if you simulate this scenario,
second step. Then the last step will be we assign the original weights into the bucket which is
There are many excellent tools to choose for fine tuning.
It keeps adding for each action the LM did.
So usually those models are huge and hard to apply
you will have this kind of trajectory.
an answer, but because this is a probability-based model, every time it will generate
You can search for them.
Actually, a later one show a very small R can do quite a good job already.
So in each state,
the, this our textbook. You can take a look at all the details of them. Here, I just list some
But here I just list some popular tools for fine tuning,
to be applied into certain edge device, for example.
This can be generating a sentence one token by one token.
remember this one, you will have state action reward.
closest to the scaled value. So we will run them into different buckets. So in this case all the
So maybe small like a few short questions. Yeah, yeah. So for the quiz, the question will only be covered topics we introduce in the second half.
a large length model fine tuning.
So after that, some optimization method
So we already talked about during Lora inference.
Those triplets to record what's the Mario's pass,
So advantage will be under this stage, all the tokens I have generated and in the future, what's the reward I get?
But you know many of them are in difficult to use.
maybe slightly different or quite different answers. But it does not know which answer
key points we want to consider. For example, this classification fine-tuning or mask LM,
need to be applied on those big models.
We just add them together.
So the inference will be significantly increased.
how it gets to the end.
So maybe if you want to do fine tuning on certain tasks,
That's why we will talk about it now.
So if we simulate this process,
values will be mapped into a four bit precision. So that's the idea of this ABS max quantization.
So this is the advantage.
are most related to the question being asked. So this means no notion of preference.
So first, the quantization.
Next, let's look at the implementation.
So you can see there are, of course there are other stuff, but you can read the details of PPO.
we can teach Mario in next time,
you may try hadn't faced or unsolved first.
it will only train the last layers, the output layers of the model. So it usually will be used
Quantization is a process of reducing
We can see this during implementation,
So the first half content you already you have already been tested. So don't need to worry about that.
what he can do is to maximize this reward
Because those tools are easy, relatively easy to use
the numerical precision of a model with and activities.
The third one is also obvious. It cannot learn from feedback because when the model is trained,
we have slightly different formula like as the previous theory part.
Of course during this process we were in order to not lose the precision. We will still store the
I won't give you too much details here, but just remember a PPO policy.
in order to go to the end of the game
We actually have introduced quantization method
and give you speed and memory improvements with not much changes on the code itself.
in classification kind of scenario. So for example, the bird for text classification is using
I will give you more information, maybe next week before the quiz. So you will understand more on the quiz. And also I need to draw your attention that because this year we are using a new quiz system examiner.
instead of touch a gongba and fail.
We add some small factors there.
it's the parameters that not change animal. So it just can produce answers. It won't give
during QLora.
This is an optimization policy for reinforcement learning.
So that's the whole learning process in a game environment.
QLora is to quantize the values of the width
For example, this alpha is scaling factor.
scaling factor. So that's the power point of those values. So we only work on the base values here.
So it's a good starting point.
this kind of fine-tuning. But for us, we were more consider about how to use parameter efficient
So this is a very famous one.
It will request four models, which is quite memory, not efficient, right?
during the parameter efficient training process.
do any learning at all. So the last one is objective misalignment. So this means
And this Lamar factory is actually a no code web interface.
This will be used to adjust the influence of this new metrics
Actually, we can learn from this process,
So the quantization generally follows the same way.
So you can also explore this one here.
this reinforcement learning process for LM alignment.
So in this way we convert all those values in big 16 or 32 bit values into four bit ones.
towards the whole original metrics.
It's complex because you are dealing with four models at the same time.
fine-tuning. That's what we're going to discuss later, which is Laura. But when you
when we train the sft, our objective function is to minimize the cross entropy, to minimize the loss.
We received a lot of complaints about the two. I will recommend you to test using the mock test to test your system first before you come in.
It's just for all the model parameters,
So those are just some references for you to refer to if you really go into fine tuning stage.
Drop out, this is a drop out rate.
So that's why instead of PPO, there are other advantages.
Let's see, the LM is an agent making decisions.
it will do the quantization to reduce its size.
This is a common strategy we were used in deep learning
For example, we can consider LM is Mario here.
So I won't go to that details on how quantization is made.
ask what kind of fine-tuning strategy there are, you may refer to this table because this chart,
Then during the inference if we want to decontextation we want to let this value come back to the
It might be a cross entropy loss, right? But this is a learning objective, but this loss does not
And this table summarizes what we talk about today.
So this table, we show some challenges of reinforcement learning using PPO.
to prevent overfitting.
So the state here, instead of this picture,
It's largely similar as QLora.
I believe you all know this in deep learning modules.
But of course, on site we will invite these IT people to come and solve your problem if there's any.
we can see the state for LM game is input prompt.
And when you face fine tuning scenario,
Just for your information, after quantization, for example,
this chart gives you a very clear illustration on what the training will adjust and what's the
original precision. We just multiply the quantized value with the scaling factor which is stored
So we won't discuss more here.
equal to the model is helpful, honest or safety. It does not do that. It just
First, as I mentioned earlier, you will need four models in memory simultaneously.
this table lists fine tuning strategy for your reference.
a seven billion model parameters,
So every time the LM gets input,
So this table here shows some empirical parameters you can start with.
But it's good for you to to to prepare first.
if it's in original IP 32 bits,
then action is the next token he gave out.
But of course this is just empirical.
Like every time you were dealing with these four models, you need to have the memory to store all the widths of these four models.
So this is just for your information.
tries to give you similar answer for the same question. So this is the whole
output of the model fine-tuning process. Just now we mentioned fine-tuning may cause catastrophic
somewhere in the memory. So we will still come back to the original precision. So that's the
it may have a 20-inch gate of size.
This is not a golden rule.
Oh, this timeline and deliverable is from top-down line. I may, I may, I didn't think with him about it, but I think we can, I can discuss with him.
Similar as the action jump left, right, this decision.
This is not the golden rule or something.
Our principle is to always start from a simplest method.
This is just a reference for you.
But after quantization, it will be reduced into 3.5G,
some key limitations after sft. Now we are in the second step. So that's
And secondly, PPO training is sensitive to hyper parameters because all the value model advantage they have, they have some parameters that drive the performance of this policy.
And the policy here is how the LM do generate the output
Our idea of choosing hyper parameter
the whole idea of quantization. Just to follow your information this ABS max is just one of the
forgetting. This means after tuning, the model doesn't remember what it needs to stay
which is significant, almost eight times reduction
So that means if you want to do something using large length model,
meters during Lora training is you can start with some
bring us the following training, further training. So that's the alignment we're going to talk about.
is the original LM width,
quantization approach. This is the simplest one. But the idea will be similar.
on the memory requirement.
default values, for example, those ones.
prompt engineering, maybe the first,
which is original large length models, right?
So that's the beauty of the quantization.
before it fine-tuning. That means it forgot the knowledge it learned. It just
Then you will tune the learning rate first
because it's free and you get instant results right.
But the quantization, the objective is
And then because we want to teach the LM to the correct,
And I think you can submit together with the whole system with the presentation and and videos.
So in the next session we'll talk about alignment. So just now we talk about
with a fixed alpha and a rank.
So it's quite sensitive.
A different quantization method is just different how they store the scales of base values.
And if you say it first, if that fails,
while we reduce the size, we don't want
minimizes losses on your training data. So that means the model is over-trained on your own data.
to human preference,
That means every time the training result cannot be predicted.
You tune the learning rate first.
you decide if rack will help need to build a database line so forth.
to reduce the performance, the accuracy.
so we will use human preference as a reward function here.
Then if until certain number of tuning you'll stand.
So there are two main approaches for model quantization.
Laura sft. The pre-trained RM even after sft may not know.
And what's the bucket distribution mechanism they use?
So that's another drawback of this PPO training.
To teach LM, you should always.
But if you need behavior changes.